honey 20 today we are to each taking a
turn if we want to talk about how can we
transition to a world without war and as
always with idea cafes are allowed to
pass and not have participate in the up
to 5 minute presentation part and just
participate in it in the conversation
out after and who would like to go first
I'll go first
alright as we were we were talking a
little bit beforehand that from my
perspective how do we transition to a
world with that war is first ending the
war that's inside ourselves or for me
specifically the ending the war that's
inside of me because there are times
when there are parts of me that are
fighting with each other and it makes it
incredibly difficult to take action in
the world and so you know really
understanding what the different parts
of me are wanting and what they are
trying to get for me and and the more I
do that the more it gives me the
patience to sit with somebody who has a
perspective that is completely different
than mine and hear them and understand
that ok what they're trying to do is
completely antithetical to how I think
that they should be doing it and yet
they're trying to get a need met and so
can I help to understand what need
they're trying to get met in order to
address how to move forward and you know
there as I am able to you know resolve
the inner conflict within me it helps me
to you know be able to resolve conflicts
with the people in the family and family
and the more I'm able to do that then
the more I can go you know the more then
the more I have a secure base from which
to go out
interact with the world and interact
with people who maybe have very
different perspectives than I do
ultimately I think it's an individual
thing you know that transition to a
world without war is comes down to my
individual you know what are the what
are the things that I can do on a daily
basis to reduce conflict both within
myself and within my interpersonal
relationships because as that is able to
transition it it ripples out it has an
effect and yeah I think that's that I'll
leave it there as always I started
talking for my mics up who would like to
go next at the raise of hands that
aren't done mic everyone just wake
everyone all right friends
I think mm-hmm I think here is where I
eat from an interpersonal point of view
and you know from a prac of practice
point of view that's something you have
to work on all the time but I don't like
this word first you know we have to do
this first it's like I think hopefully
we can agree that we always um want to
try and do both things at the same time
right it's kind of paradoxical but we
want to work on ourselves and on the
system and those two are related but my
more general approach what I want to try
to bring in today is to see the idea of
being anti-war itself like I tweeted the
other day like and beaten anti-war is
like the easiest thing and the hardest
thing because first you have to make the
decision to commit to it which I think a
lot of people want to do in principle
but I don't I don't think you can do if
you're in a military or engaged in
something like that but then in my tweet
I said and then and then the and then
the moderates come for you right because
that the problem is not just the warp
the warmongers right that's a bit
reductionist but there's you know
there's there's liberals and
conservatives that go to war but the
problem is like like with the Iraq war
like it was the moderates that tipped
the scales that bought in to the
fear-mongering and the lies that execute
that carried out an institutional you
know a scale war right and so so the
moderates that went along with it have
have have a reckoning to do right they
have to understand how they contributed
to that ongoing kind of just tradition
if you will of wars the status quo right
but to be really at you know to to
transition to a world without war
incrementalism has been kind of the name
of the game right like let's let's you
know have a world police trying to
minimize conflict but then you have
blowback from all those activities right
so I think a game B approach has to have
a higher standard right like there's
always been anti-war activists but it
hasn't always been that practical and
the discussion between Jordan Hall and
and BJ Campbell yesterday was pretty
interesting on this point because they
talked a lot about just kind of the you
know structural game theoretical things
that lead countries to war it makes it
kind of unavoidable right and this is
all this is all true historically but in
our moment we're not just being idealist
but we you know it's it's a different
game that we're trying to play and the
technology the global communication
infrastructure uh makes makes war uh you
know less and less viable less and less
attractive so let's relate it to
current events right the Iran situation
all the serious leftists all the Bernie
surrogates like myself are against war
with Iran mm-hmm because it doesn't make
any sense and and in Trump's actions in
this regard er you know extrajudicial
and kind of you know white whitewashing
issue you know calling the e the guy a
terrorist when you know um in fact what
he is is a government official right uh
and and you could say the same thing
about American people in like Dick
Cheney or Donald Rumsfeld mmm and they
made this point on on majority report
this morning I just finished watching it
so uh yeah I think that's all I have to
say it's just that you know we we have
to take this kind of principled
commitment to anti-war as a precondition
for uh answering the question all right
thanks Brent would either Bentley or
Eric like to go next
Eric wants to go next probably works out
well if he might be stepping out so yeah
I mean I think I can be fairly quick
here I mean III broadly agree that war
in the outside world doesn't end while
you know each of us is is that confident
in conflict with ourselves I do all ii
think a couple of things there's a
couple of things that I wanted to bring
to this firstly what we actually mean by
war because if but if by war you simply
mean armed conflict with weapons on a
large scale between you know to to large
groups then yeah they're this is this is
a bit but I think it runs much much much
much deeper than that which is kind of I
think what Kyra was alluding to that
pretty much every activity we engage in
on an international on a global scale is
a form of warfare right politics is a
form of warfare you know there that it's
deeply deeply deeply rooted in
everything that we do and I and I think
the identification by the game be
thought people if you like that over
rival ristmas is one of the key key
key key underlying destructive dynamics
that exists within game a there's
obviously the ultimate evolution of
rivalries dynamics is war but a bit as I
say I think we play it out in many many
many many many different ways not just
in terms of armed conflict but that on
the streets of armed conflict while the
tools of war exist while there are
weapons and tanks and machine guns and
so on and so on and so on sooner or
later someone is going to use them right
you know you can't get rid of these
things unilaterally if you you know if
you're the only one without any guns
well yeah this is a silly position to be
an equal if you're the only one with
guns yeah there's nothing stopping you
from running rampant over everything so
III do think that the while the tools of
war exist war will continue to exist and
I don't see any way of getting rid of
the tools of war you can't uninvent
stuff you can't unring these bells and
so I I kind of feel that war might be
something that we're stuck with and all
we can do is somehow seek to limit the
worst of its effects and I think that's
all I have to say I will fight you Erik
[Laughter]
would you like to share yeah yeah I
appreciate what you've all said care
about working on personally that's I've
been on a journey for that and that's
been very important because we can't
really help other people or not if we
don't have the fortitude to do it and
Brent was saying about everything and
Eric that's definitely a challenge the
part I would like to bring in is that
it's very difficult at times to make
just good decisions that's kind of one
of my passions and so you know if you
look back at just after 9/11 the United
States it was very close to unanimous to
go to war by our government officials
and by many people in the States
I wore on things I like doing is working
on tools that'll let us take a step back
and take a look at these things you know
without letting our emotions take over
which goes back to what you know what
Kara was saying about being able to
regulate those to some extent and
understand them and feel them properly
but also having tools that help us take
in this large amount of information that
we have for lots of different places and
be able to synthesize that in a way that
our brains can can actually make use of
as opposed to summarizing and and making
large biases there always be small
biases but kind of reducing that bias
for those using tools like that I think
that could help us in future decisions
about or and then you know so that's
that's kind of that desert that's all I
had to add on it all right thanks
Bentley I will take my turn now I did a
video on November 11th which is our
remembrance day here on how we can
actually obtain a world without war and
then well Bentley was talking I realized
that the war I'm talking about is very
much the systemic countries fighting
each other is what I would define is
were like people in power using big
weapons to fight each other on a massive
scale
and that there are two types of four one
of which has fought for profit and it's
most of the war that's going on right
now and other war that has fought for
ideology that would be like Isis is kind
of fighting a war of ideology and I
think both of those can be fought
whatever the fight war like stock water
with information and empowerment of the
people that how we stop the ones that
are done for profit is to take their
profit away I don't buy land mines so I
can't pick the best of land mines to buy
but I guarantee you
everyone who sits on those boards
everyone who's a CEO everyone who's the
CFO also is on boards and has their
money in every other industry and having
the information laid out so that we can
boycott them to the nth degree
I mean their kids don't go to our
schools we do not buy any of their
products we do not we would put an end
to war in three months less than three
months once it hits them in their wallet
which is the reason they're paint
they're playing it there isn't a war
left anymore now the ideology one is a
different position to fight because
those people aren't doing it for profit
but the army the people that are
actually doing the fighting and putting
their bodies on the line are generally
very desperate people and so once you
have access to food and clothing and
shelter it's a lot harder to turn you
into a murderer it's a lot harder to
convince you that these people are your
enemy and that is another place where we
fight or is things like this idea Cafe
creating platforms that connect the
world not just that we're connected but
truly connected that these wars these
things that Trump have done in the last
few months there was like the Kurdish
genocide that he basically helped move
forward I don't know when exactly did to
do that he pulled people out of was
fighting them and one of my good friends
is Kurdish and one of my good friends
who just cut my hair is is was born in
Iran and having neighbors that are
actually and friends that are actually
part of these like that are directly
affected by and have family members that
are directly affected by it changes
things it's a lot harder to turn an
entire group of people into the enemy
when you are participating in
conversation with them nothing
necessarily to do with war you know book
clubs you can have you know play music
together whatever it happens to be the
more we connect to the globe on that
level I think the the more we have
access to not being to not have anymore
and then what Kira talked about that
that that personal piece the knowing
when we're at war more with ourselves
and when I'm like trying to be in
dominance
/ someone or allowing someone to be in
dominant so for me just like owning
those emotions but I think that can only
be done to a certain degree until bring
groups or in groups working on projects
for in groups with it with a mission
being able to figure out that conflict
because I can figure out my
interpersonal conflict but that when
someone else is involved is a whole
other level and once we figure out those
two pieces not that and then it's all at
the same time it's like once we have
actual empowerment of groups and access
to the information we don't leave it up
to our government officials to stop
going to war we stop going to war and we
therefore we don't just even port out
into the street we boycott them to the
nth degree it's like no we're not gonna
if Starbucks is investing in landmines
in a month say they are we don't buy
stuff from Starbucks and wait if 10% of
people were doing that truly put their
money where their mouth is and stop
supporting war war would change
overnight and I don't know if I'm taking
five minutes but I will I will end there
and everyone can get unpause I don't
know I just wanted to check with can I
just ask you Bentley you mentioned that
after 9/11 the country was almost
unanimously behind war does that were
you trying to suggest that in a
circumstance like that where everybody
agrees that it's okay well I don't think
we have a choice of everyone thinks it's
okay to do it okay I mean that's who
makes the decision right the people no I
think that if we had the right tools to
look at the facts at the time we did for
some people I don't know we didn't want
to constantly have the information I
don't want to contradict your point too
much but but there was people that were
right about it and that's what matters
right now on this topic right we need to
listen to the people who were right at
the time Michael Moore Bernie Sanders
like hundreds hundreds of people and and
the populace - right it's not like it
was more it was
are the government pushing right and not
the Elector itself and then the people
were given no choice right two years
after 9/11 and the Iraq plans were
already made in the project for a new
American Century documents right so
there is momentum behind this and people
were just lied to right so we can't we
can't in any way like really rationalize
it after the fact we should we shouldn't
what I'm saying is that those those
people that had the right information
did not have a tool to make that
information clear to most everyone else
I mean in what happened in the US within
the UK there was a BBC reporter came out
and said this whole dossiers been sexed
up there are no weapons of mass
destruction and the I have a very very
reliable source yeah absolutely this is
all bullshit right and the government
here set up an entire link entire
inquiry to exonerate the government
castigate the BBC and everything that
was reported later turned out to be true
and so you know and and more than a
million people turned out on the streets
of London to say no the war in Iraq is
wrong it's illegal bla bla bla bla bla
bla bla none of this shit made any
difference yeah the decision was made
the day 9/11 happened or probably even
before one of the what's coming up for
me and as everyone was sharing was the
concept of the war on sense-making and
when we bring it back to okay the way
that we were making sense of the world
at that time did not produce the results
that we wanted Brent there may have been
some people who knew and yet there is
still a lack of trust in in some of
those people in a large portion of the
population and so how do you how do how
do we take into account that war on
sense-making that that the way that we
have historically made sense of the
world all of those tools no longer work
and how you and so exactly going back to
what Bentley said of they may have known
but they didn't have the effective tools
either interpersonal the or
technological wise to disseminate that
information and the rest of the
population didn't know how to make sense
of it yeah and it's no different today
right and that's why it's important like
there's still a war on sense-making and
and and there's still a lot of
disagreement about what happened in 2016
and what's happened since then right and
it goes back to what Eric was saying
mm-hmm which is actually a point that
Foucault really really lobbied for and
that's that you know politics is just an
extension of war it's there's there's a
way a way to look at it that you know
you you can understand how they're
entangled and it is a kind of postmodern
process mm-hmm even though Foucault
wasn't a strictly a postmodernist to
disentangle to deconstruct that
relationship between more in politics
right and now we're in this moment we
need to go beyond that can I ask for a
little bit of clarification disentangle
okay so can you bring it down into a
maybe more concrete example than war in
politics because usually as something
like that can be applied to like I'm
trying to I'm trying to understand what
what you're saying exactly and I don't
fully I don't fully crack it and so I'm
trying to yeah no I'm not I'm not super
clear on your question either okay so he
so you said Foucault said that we need
to do angle war from politics or so I
guess I guess maybe the first question
would be what what is what does he mean
or what do you mean by politics in this
situation so that that expression goes
back to a kind of war theorist named
Klaus bits who said that
something like war is you know politics
by other means something like that like
it was a famous kind of excerpt from his
treatise on more and then Foucault
inverted it and said well politics is is
war by other means or something like
that like at the end of the day it
doesn't matter because it's a kind of um
you know they're they're they're
statements that you know kind of try to
cancel each other out mm-hmm but but
this idea is that like there's all these
factors behind war it's not just
resources it's not just ideology it's
all of these things and and as society
becomes more abstract right and less
less violent statistically like a lot
Pinker hmm
you know the modalities of of conflict
get repressed right and then they get
they get sublimated into into trade
deals and foreign policy and all these
all these weird you know Byzantine
policies and we need to get we need to
move away from that in the other
direction just towards more like
pragmatic peaceful initiatives right it
comes back to like realism versus
idealism paranoia versus Metanoia like
what you know do do we look at other
countries like Iran as friends or
enemies right and Jubilee has friends
from Moran I have friends from Iran like
I don't see any countries in the world
as state threats to to my livelihood or
to global security but the u.s.
perpetuates that narrative right because
it's in their interest to do so and I
think they do themselves a disservice
whether its conservatives or kind of
liberal Hawks like Hillary Clinton they
do themselves a disservice by just
toeing the line of traditional neocon
foreign policy like we need to enter a
new kind of phase of global politics
especially now more than ever because of
things like climate you know climate
change being an existential threat to
everyone we need to move in the opposite
direction
what does that look like what does it
actually look like in the opposite
direction like things that maybe we
could do or like the current because the
issue is a lot of what war is is our
political elites that we've
theoretically elected going to war with
one another when often it isn't the will
of the people people don't want to go to
war how do we actually transition to a
world without war going back to my my
opening point like we need to elect the
anti-war candidates like for real and
not just the ones that say they're
anti-war but we need to vet those that
that track record in those policies and
elect those people that's that's just
the political dimension that's one
dimension one of my kind of favorite
theories and approaches I wanted to be a
little more prepared with today but but
I'm not
um is you know as I said going in the
opposite direction of war what that
looks like visa vie the
military-industrial complex is there's
this concept of a peace industrial
complex and if you map out what the
military-industrial excetera
complex is which I've done partially and
you map out the research about it then
you have a pretty good map of what game
a kind of protocols and beliefs look
like right and and and and where the
investment is right and I love your
point about divestment Jubilee like this
is a key thing right like with the Iran
assassination you know defense stocks
spiked a little bit right it's because
you know the military-industrial complex
profits from this that's that's their
organizing principle we need to save
those people we need to liberate them
from their you know defense contracting
world by by a divesting and investing in
a peace industrial complex which which
needs you know we talk about scalability
the peace industrial complex like the
military-industrial complex is scaled
its global it's ubiquitous we need to
scale civil society you know universal
basic income there's a whole host of
things that we talk about in these in
these circles and communities that that
can converge on that kind of abstraction
of a piece industrial complex and and
there's there's people that have done
great work on it you know that's the
kind of stuff I'd like to to to
foreground and unpack more ya know I
love the idea of a piece industrial
complex
I mean I for me personally I don't think
our first step is is um the elected part
because everything elected just runs
very slowly and it's a lot of work
people in power who might not be able to
do anything anyway but we're in the
middle of an election like in the u.s.
like it has to be um yes I would like
them America especially to in left
someone that's not war however also is
America ever going to elect anyone who's
not war like if it were 490 like how
many years out of what they've been in
in existence for yeah right okay so why
do people why does Jordan Hall talk
about a religion that's not a religion
or whatever or why do people you know
castigate social justice as religion if
we can't have a type of secular faith in
peace in the peace process like
everyone's talking about spirituality
and faith where is the faith in this
ultimate it's a attractor that we want
in peace like if is that not what
religions are peace not that we're gonna
get there through electing new
government officials right but it but it
matters that's all I'm saying like we
can't can't we can't neglect it we can't
abdicate our responsibility and and you
know Bernie Sanders says himself like
like you know his slogan is not me us
but he really means like putting him in
the power in itself is not the solution
you know when the candidate himself is
telling you that like I'm not gonna save
you you know I think it's there's
there's there's a deep truth behind that
because he's an organizer and trying to
rally a
masses of people to cease their their
political power to transform the system
right it's not just about people voting
and their self-interest either it's
about you know if we have any kind of
leverage in any particular election
let's try to maximize it right let's
let's try to win and the left didn't win
in 2016 because there was two factions
fighting it out an establishment one and
an insurgent actual progressive a kind
of locus within the you know a you know
really actually outside the demek
Democratic Party but trying to take it
over now now we have a chance at a
replay so I think we should do you know
do the right thing people should
converge rather than fighting and some
of the candidates are converging you
know is to me like voting I don't know
like we spend so much of our
conversations meaning in the world that
is telling me the game bSpace talking
about politics and politics at Harvey
podium we get one vote in four years
whereas the actions we can take we can
actually create a peace industrial
complex we don't need our governments to
do it
we can do it and therefore we don't need
to go through the job of electing
someone if we had a million people
putting $10 a month into a pool and we
were using that money to say hey where's
where's the project is gonna be the most
piece generating and chose to do that
and chose to put our human hours instead
of going in an army to be like yes where
do you need me you want me to dig a
ditch I'm there digging a ditch we could
easily do that but we the fact that we
put our saag like we put this tower onto
other people like someone else has to
solve it and spend all of our time
talking about the politics when like we
have we don't really have power as one
individual all of our power comes in
groups and yet we have supreme powering
groups and to be able to get that piece
organized is how we get to peace is how
we get to abundance and out and Jubilee
how do we get to the the question that
comes into my mind is how do we get that
cohesion within groups to be able to do
you know the and and and how do you
create the trust you know when there's a
when there's a disaster an earthquake or
our you know a tsunami or whatever in
the world you know almost everybody will
will is willing to text to the Red Cross
there are $10 to give them because they
have built up the trust that their that
you know their money is going to go to
the places that it needs to go that they
have that coordination and so but I
think going back to what the the thing I
was talking about earlier of the war on
sense-making there is a profound lack of
trust in our society not just with our
politicians but with individuals there
are only a very few number of people
that I deeply trust in my life and but I
have spent most of the last few years
focusing on how do I build that trust
and part of that is when somebody who
you know when when someone that in my
life shares something that where our
views are diametrically opposed that can
feel incredibly threatening to me and I
want to change their mind and I want to
convince them that they're wrong and
making peace with that threat that I
feel and being learning how to hold both
their their reality and my reality in my
head at the same time in order and and
the the discomfort that I feel of
holding both of those things at the same
time too in order to get to the place
where there's trust where Trust is built
and so like how do we build that type of
you know system Brett I hear what you're
saying about Bernie I don't I don't
trust politicians period like doesn't
matter what they represent I don't trust
them I trust people that I know impress
people who
we'll listen to my perspective and hear
me and so creating you know how building
that you know I think there is amazing
organization with politicians and if we
took that and married that with like the
ability like a more of a listening to
build that trust then I could think we
could go towards the direction of what
Jubilees talking about and so I don't
know that's the it's both of those
pieces because I yeah I don't I just you
know good bad or indifferent
unilaterally I don't trust someone who
identifies as a politician I don't trust
and and I'm I'm trying to be a little
bit more open to someone who is
advocating for a politician I'm like I
don't know if I trust you either
but being open to it it's like you know
I have my bias that says that's person
not to be trusted
I'm trying to be open to that being
something that can change I have thought
him on that issue but Bentley just son
paused himself so I feel like he all
right you did so I feel like yeah I mean
I was I was thinking that yeah building
trust between people is important I
would think that if we have really good
processes and tools in place that having
trust in those or being able to inspect
everything and have trust because you
and the people that that you trust have
looked at the information once it's laid
out in a very methodical and useful way
and I don't the problem with trusting
people that haven't put all those facts
into some sort of process is that it's
always open to unknown biases so I think
there's a lot of room we have on you
know making spreadsheets for decisions
is kind of a way of staying it that we
don't we are brain
cannot does not have the power to
consume all the facts about these things
that's just who we are at our limit so
without a tool it's not possible to do
it accurately although we can get lucky
most of the time but so I would rather
trust in processes than individuals but
Trust is an important part because
people won't take collective action
without trust can I reply to that first
of all like I'm completely with you Kyra
like on the other nut not trusting
politicians like that that's where I'm
coming from as a place of skepticism and
cynicism and you know criticism of
traditional politics you know I mean
I've always been kind of a Green Party
candidate a kind of person but but the
green parties have always been very weak
in North America right and that's that's
a whole different conversation like like
there's there's a hegemony of the status
quo right that makes it hard to change
and in some parts of the world green
parties are successful in there and
they're succeeding and executing their
policies hmm I totally forgot I was
gonna say - Bentley's point and I think
Eric had something he was gonna say yeah
I did and at the risk of sounding the
risk of sounding a bit dismissive of
some of what's been said I think this
notion of that wall goes away if people
just talk to each other and trust each
other more I I think it's kind of
somewhat absurd and naive because you
know the average person in the street
the vast vast vast majority of people I
think I can fairly safely say never want
Ward you know what I mean it's just
certainly not in their own backyard you
know I mean nobody ever wants it and yet
we go to war again and again and again
because the fact of the matter is a
prime minister or a president can
declare war doesn't matter at all what
the country thinks and there's already a
couple of million soldiers whatever
tools and arms and tanks and planes and
whatever ready to fly them to wherever
immediately so I think the whole notion
of war being got rid of while we
maintain a system of nay
and government I think I think is a is
an absurd and naive hope I also think we
don't get rid of it with nations and and
borders and such but it's transitioning
to a world with without that which is
about figuring out how do we trust one
another
Bonita Roy just put something and
amazing the game be space about like
this is the polarization of the left and
the right and you know we need to she's
said it way better but there was this
idea that came to me on what she wrote
where I'm like when my kid look is
playing with someone for social play
with son for two hours I don't even
learned their name I'm like what's their
day I don't know it's like we're just
playin it on time for that but like
shouldn't ask for their ideology right
it's like do you want to play this they
don't need to necessarily have the trust
they don't need to have and so figuring
out how do we working groups together
without needing to agree on the thing
right can we agree the project needs to
get me right up or cooling what I said
if we're doing a piece global industrial
complex whatever was called I'm putting
ten dollars in and we're voting on
what's the most important project your
project might not get funded right your
project maybe there's two and you wanted
really wanted one well there's also an
option to just split it and be like well
you people work on this one and you
people work on that one that there are
ways to work around while still owning
right there is that tension we all have
when someone disagrees with us like how
can we get to gaming B without needing
to agree on what game B is how do we get
to game B by having any when we have
fundamentally different needs and wants
so I kind of owning that and figuring
out how do we work together right in
small groups that grow and allow for
that trust to be built but also allow
for the trust being done and Fred sheets
because I don't trust the Red Cross I
don't think they're the best source of
disaster relief I might give them ten
bucks because they're something but
they're like us having something where I
can see I can see transparently where
that money's going and then after the
first disaster we critique that and say
here's what could have been done better
so the next one's even better
and the next one's even better so we
have the ability to go in and set up a
whole new city right away when refugees
have to leave right it would people
whether it's form or or climate change
we've come up with solutions to the
problems without needing to first get
along
but I want to build a build on all of
that because I think it ties into
Bentley's point about process and for me
that the process we should be fostering
is demilitarization right like people
don't even talk about that enough but
but to unpack it and define it and
execute it as a process we work towards
and I've written about this concept
called normative incrementalism where we
overcome social paradoxes by agreeing to
work towards that attractor right in
this case game B so the process we
should be working on is demilitarization
because there is a process of
militarization that that is the logic
dictating you know how a lot of politics
goes and how a lot of money is spent um
mmm and well I just quickly want to
throw out a statistic that goes back to
what we were talking about with the Iraq
war
mmm yeah this is from like 12 years ago
so I don't remember the source but I saw
a statistic when I was studying that 96
percent of international relations
scholars were against the Iraq war right
does that does the mainstream media tell
you that you know do those guys go on TV
as kind of analysts and and and share
that not so much right because of the
hegemony of um you know the the power
Lee in this case a pushing for war so
that's I mean that's something we have
to be cognizant of all throughout
history and on your point Jubilee about
the Red Cross like a hundred percent
know where you're coming from I know
people have worked for the Red Cross or
the UN and they're totally disillusioned
because those organizations are are just
functional and corrupt and this speaks
to a non geared artist is thisis that
all of you know corporate philanthropy
and stuff it's all co-opted it all gets
fed back into game a and and and we need
to realize that and get ahead of the
problem right by through divestment and
through different types of organizations
and etc um and then the last thing I
want to say is about is about trust just
to kind of finish my thought with that
like like we should be distrustful of
politics of course and in the media and
how its presented and we should not
necessarily trust our own institutions
are our own intuitions about things but
when you actually examine and scrutinize
somebody like Bernie and his track
record and his movement sorry he's been
a lifelong anti-war advocate and not
only that like he's done it correctly
he's embodied the communication
protocols and and peaceful gestures and
all that kind of stuff he does it he
wins hearts and minds if you just give
him the time in documentaries or books
or in the daily discourse that's going
on in in that in that movement through
publications like the intercept or
whatever like there's a law there is on
one hand there's a lot of mockery of
right-wingers and stuff like that but on
the other hand like when you really get
into the weeds of Bernie's movement he
himself is is a pretty good negotiator
and peacemaker there's a lot of
Republicans that like him he gets a lot
of amendments passed and he consistently
votes the American conscious right
he alone opposed Trump's military budget
when all these other candidates just
went along with it you know when your
job as a politician gives you that power
to vote yes or no on things you know you
got to make some calculations about the
long game but but by and large we should
all be committing to doing the right
thing up front which is opposed opposing
war opposing the endless funding of the
military-industrial complex right we're
taught that we're talking about taxpayer
dollars going into objects and weapons
that that are money pits they never get
used and when they do used they're often
misapplied and it kills innocent play
you keep bringing it back to politics
thank you trying to work in politics and
foreign politics very clearly like
intertwined but like what you talk about
is the media right the media doesn't
necessarily support Bernie we can
disagree on whether Bernie's the best
person to be in charge of the United
States but we could
agree on how do we redo the media so we
can trust someone write the imbd for
politicians the wiki election week
raised on Saturday is one such project
right it does not be that project but a
project that makes sense of who do we
trust in politics the most not because
the media tells us to and where they get
their money from but like we've created
something that we can we can we can
trust and that is where like maybe we
don't need we need to have a distrust
right like I might trust you as an
individual but it's more about trusting
the process and the group right like if
you can see it and it's transparent I we
can fight all day about whether Bernie's
the best person for for the or we could
step back and be like which I agree with
I would love in charge of it but like
finding the how do we look for the truth
how do we have that moron sense making
without being in a debate right like how
do we distrust information so that we
can all use it because all the
information that's in your head Brent is
your information right for me to be able
to trust it I have to know you I have to
trust you I have to know your
sense-making if it's laid out in front
of us you don't need that you don't need
to spend the time and energy saying it
repeatedly it's like oh I can see
Bernie's track record you're like we
don't need to argue it it's right there
in front of me there's nothing to argue
yeah I wanted to circle back and ask
Bentley about you know you said about
trusting the processes more than
trusting people at least that was my
what I what I thought I heard you say
and so so please correct me if that's if
that's wrong and I want to understand
that because I mean it's ultimately I'm
going to trust you know my husband more
than I am going to trust someone you
know a random stranger off of the street
I'm gonna trust his opinion more because
I have a I have a more accurate you know
I have I have a track record with him I
know that that he's somebody that I can
trump that that I think that his opinion
I can trust on most things they're his
choice of music maybe not so much
but and so like that I'm trying to I I
want to understand your perspective
because that that's that that was one
that kind of found my brain went huh I
don't understand well it's kind of like
who would you trust more if your husband
hadn't looked at the bank account for a
month on what the dollar amount is at
your bank account or your bank's website
so the bank's website is is the process
as a system as opposed to your memory or
your husband's memory of all the
deposits and withdrawals you've made
since you started the account that's
what that's the piece that we don't have
for this type of decision-making that
we're trying to make on these current
problems we're doing it all out of our
brains and our memories and our
interpretations we don't have a written
process of evaluating that information
and synthesizing a decision so that's
the tool I'm working on okay there are
no current tools that do that
I like that example that makes sense
yeah I'm gonna have to show just that
one okay thank you yeah I can try to add
to that because I agree the the process
and is important and I'll try to avoid
politics but it's um you know all all of
this overlaps but the idea of process
obviously is super important but the
question is what process right so what
comes to mind it for me is two things
one is technocracy right technocracy is
all about process and it's this kind of
you know it's about bureaucracy and
rationalization and and having
hierarchies and kind of distributed
sense-making right i mean that's what we
have already uh and and and you know
things like the UN are supposed to
support that but there's there's too
much tension between the kind of global
order and the american-led
you know very
of that hmm um and then so so there's
tons and tons of critiques of
technocracy going back the the whole
last century it's it's a really
brilliant discourse because it's um you
know it subverts it this it continues
the the kind of postmodern trend if you
will of subverting the Enlightenment you
know pointing out how the Enlightenment
goes into totalitarianism and then to
bureaucracy and technocracy and all this
but you know Elizabeth Warren is a
technocratic Obama is a technocrat
people who judge as a technocratic
meaning that they they they are very
process-oriented
right but by and large they're nested in
the a certain type of status quo process
where they're being pulled from all
sides and they don't really have a moral
compass of their own they try to their
their you know nominally pretty good
people but but there's a lot lot of
hypocrisy there like like I said with
being an anti-war activist in the
military like like like Pete Buddha
judge um you know went went to went to
war which some call just a photo-op
which which it may or may not have been
it doesn't matter because he's not
anti-war and the end to be truly
anti-war is such a complex like highly
ethical you know position to take up so
what is the answer to detect ocker see
right what is the antidote to that I
think it's this other process that I'm
alluding to that that you know going
back to the civil rights movement Martin
Luther King and every progressive a kind
of leader that that has followed in his
footsteps are about a different type of
process than the technocratic one uh so
we need to understand the difference
there what is the other process called
is it called somewhere I'm trying to
avoid politics it's called Bernie
Sanders but going going back to this
idea of trust
like Anthony Giddens is a famous
sociologist and he said Trust is the
lifeblood of modernity and this is back
in the 90s right and and you know in the
post 9/11 age we've had virtually no
trust and you know Obama was like a new
hope and then you know the financial
crisis is what he inherited and didn't
handle that satisfactorily for virtually
anybody except the banks mm-hmm so you
know again what is the process there
he's being a technocrat he's being a
compromiser a satisficer all these types
of things and you know I give Obama and
the benefit of the doubt he did the best
job he could and he appeased a ton of
people so he could remain popular except
he was constantly under attack from
people like Trump right like you're on
politics and also in our last 10 wins
what I was I really do we're supposed to
be doing um just to end by the hour so I
always say I'm going to that I doubt so
let's take our we can each wrap it up
for two minutes unless anyone has any
closing questions or thoughts they want
other people to I do have one closing
question for Bentley going back to that
processing process example just is that
my brains trying to wrap it wrap my head
around it so the example that popped
into my head is say I woke up one
morning and my account was overdrawn by
a thousand dollars like all the money
had been taken out and it said that it
was came out of you know that it had
been withdrawn by my husband's you know
debit card I trust if he tells me that
he didn't do that I would question the
bank before I would question him I would
question that that maybe our account had
been hacked before I would question here
yeah because it's an open system you can
then look and see the inside you would
know when to question that system and so
that's that's a good failsafe is that
our intuitions is a safety check on the
system right but but if I didn't have
that trust with with my husband's attend
I with him I wouldn't necessarily have
the intuition to question that
yeah yeah there there needs to be trust
between people as well and large groups
of people and also you kind of build a
trust in people as they put inputs into
the system you can see that they're
putting wise inputs so we could probably
take that off a line that you like and
get the more detail but that's that's a
very valuable insight I'll give my
closing remarks last so I can as always
so you can think about YouTube
I'll pass so other people can give any
closing remarks all right I'll just say
you know if if steven pinker is right
and we are already on a path to ending
war I mean then we have nothing to worry
about right but but I'm a critic of
people like Pinker along with many
others for being you know more than a
bit myopic and sticking his head in the
sand about you know what's really going
around going on around the world with
existential threats and with you know
progressive movements to to overcome
that and I'll just double down on my
point that like we need to commit to
anti-war while also continuously being
self-critical about about about that
about that process and I think I mean
cuz I've been I've been deeply buried in
a lot of research for the past decade
along these lines and it's it's it's a
lonely path because a lot a lot of good
stuff is out there but it's not even
talked about yet you know cuz we're
still on that kind of sense-making path
towards some of those ideas that have
been out there for a long time thank you
Eric you wanna close all marks sure I'll
go um I think you know I think Eric
maybe you had mentioned it being naive
to focus my perception it being naive to
focus on the individual because what if
if these systems are still there that
nothing's going to change and
probably a distortion of what you said
the thing that I have to ask the thing I
asked myself on a daily basis is what do
I have the power to change and I can
have all of these conversations but
unless I am able to build trust with
someone in order to you know could to
take action in the world then it you
know that is the thing I have the
ability to affect and I find these
conversations interesting and at the
same time there's a part of me that kind
of goes okay this just feels forgive my
forgive this language but like a lot of
mental masturbation of trying to solve
these problems that we can't that we
can't actually solve it in thought and
you take action by by taking action with
people that you trust that's right I
will come back to that time and time
again of what is it that I have the
ability to change in my day to day life
and how do i how do i affect that and
the the best way I know how to affect
that is by building trust with people in
order to take action
Magnus Eric yeah I've got a few things
first here is a bit of a distortion
because I'm actually all about the
individual that's that that's where my
whole thing is when there are enough
individuals then things change as a
consequence of that so that's that
that's actually my whole thing but I do
feel that in a way as you said it's a
form of masturbation because it's a
pointless conversation because as things
currently stand
you know while part of the narratives to
elect a president is how good a
commander-in-chief is he going to be you
know what I mean
this this whole thing is a fundamental
way in which we evaluate the suitability
of somebody for office right is their
ability to fight wars how good are they
going to be in a fight so you know I I
do think that war does not end until
there are just no one around who's
prepared to sign up to be a
soldier and there's no one around who's
prepared to shoot a gun out of somebody
else you know what I mean
and and that is the only way that war
stops and so yes it's all about the
individual but trying to attack systems
while the systems have all the guns and
one guy in charge can let loose all the
guns whenever they want it just seems to
me to be absurd the notion of moving to
a world without war is is it will be a
byproduct of moving to a world full of
actualized people right that it's not a
goal in and of itself it will be a
byproduct of a more meaningful goal
that's that's kind of where I'm at
thanks Eric um
Remzi also give you a chance to if you
want a closing remark even though you
haven't actually he spoke of it yet in
this idea Kevin like what Eric just said
and but one of the things that didn't
really hear the conversation was the the
war is a structure as a is a structural
issue it affords until it's like any
other game of sport parsnip let's think
of like American football right you've
got two teams who are coming and they're
playing by specific set of rules and you
don't expect somebody one of the players
to have a gun in their pocket and then
shoot somebody and kill them and why
because there are are going to be
consequences from within the rules of
the game and so there's other higher
authorities as it were that are
controlling those rules of the game and
but that don't necessarily benefit those
individuals were making the rules
meaning the outcome of the game is going
to be dependent upon clear rules that
everyone's already pre decided to find
and so and because there's no group of
people who are in power we're going to
cheat and allow that person to shoot
somebody dead or grab the ball and
circumvent those rules in and play
outside of the rules for their own
advantage means that they can't and so
the the solution is structural and and
so the game a as we've been talking
about is structural in what is that it's
property its land its resources and so
humans have always been fighting over
land and resources I know this because
we're
was born we were in the crux of the
crosshairs of Catholicism and in and in
the Islam world and we've always had to
change religion base to join whatever
team was to our advantage
so that we can survive and so but if we
are to be able to prevent war there's
got to be some level of only
individualized power but that there is
overall a group set of rules that no one
no there's no larger Authority or group
Authority like a nation who cancer can
be an authority to change the rules and
in to go out play outside those rules
that's what we have today I mean we just
violated the rules by assassinating
somebody so that means there are no
rules and so until we change the actual
explode consequences to breaking them
but yeah of course they're always going
to be consequences but it's a power
dynamic Eric as we all know but needless
to say so until we identify a new nation
that neuters power down to the
individual level and then we trust the
game then it's okay you I don't trust
people I never will I don't care you
know as some of course we you want to be
able to trust people but you only trust
them so far as you know that they can
play by the rules and that they're bound
by the rules as soon as somebody's not
bound by the rules then you can't trust
them anymore and then and then it
changes the dynamic of the game you know
if you watch any of the gangster movies
I mean it's like a classic example of
you know having rules and not having
rules and Wars is another byproduct of
that and so none that's never gonna
change until we get clear rules
regarding property resources how all of
that is valued and distributed and once
we do that then we can figure out the
governance part but until we do there's
not going to be any solution to war ever
want a chance to do those are marks
right Mike thanks for coming
no I don't know anything at all great
thanks everyone
all right thank you um my closing
remarks I was there kind of talking to
Keira now she's gone so but she said
about the mental masturbation
I think these conversations are how we
create world peace I think that that
that individual piece of meditation
doing whatever work that you do
personally to deal with you with being
as anti-war and pro peace as you can
individually and then working in groups
part of which is conversation and yet
she's right we need to be able to take
action and I think we are taking action
all of us have projects and stuff that
we are doing to take action part of my
action is these conversations is
organizing them figuring them out
figuring out how do we have
conversations with a hopefully
broadening diversity right like right
now this is game B but let's have people
it like completely different or parallel
to game B and completely against it as
part of part of the conversation how can
we work together in the in those realms
those are life some of my closing
remarks next week is my birthday so I'm
going to hold hold the idea cafe two
hours earlier so that I have more of the
day to do things in because I still want
to do this this is the way I want to
spend my birthday and I don't yet know
what the questions gonna be but I'm
gonna pick one that is fun for me to
discuss and hopefully fun for the people
that discuss and hopefully it works to
do it two hours earlier and now I'm
going to say goodbye to YouTube